hey it's professor dave, let's talk sig figs
humans have a need to communicate
their experiences with one another
how far apart are two cities? when did
something happen
and how long before it happens again? this is
why we developed
units of measurement. some correlate with
natural phenomena
like a day or year which are based on
the motion of the earth
but many are arbitrary like most units
of length and mass.
when we participate in measurement we
have to be aware of some limitations
for example how many people are in this
crowd? can we say
10,000? what about 10,400 or 10,472
we have to be careful not to make an
estimate that is more precise
than our measuring abilities allow so
when we use measuring devices
we only estimate one digit further than
the level of precision
inherent in the instrument. here we can estimate
2.33 centimeters but not 2.33481
we do not have access to that level of precision
so any measurement will have a certain amount
of significant figures or sig figs
associated with it that display how
precise it is
here are the rules for determining how
many sig figs are in a value
one: any digit that's not zero
is significant
two: zeros in between other non-zero digits
are significant
three: leading zeros, ones that come before
the first non-zero digit
are not significant
and four: trailing zeros, the ones that come
after the last non-zero digit are only
significant if they are decimal zeros
so 10,000 only has one significant
figure which really means it's about
10,000 not exactly ten thousand. if we
bring back that same crowd and one more
person shows up
can we estimate ten thousand and one? no,
because we have only estimated to one sig fig
so anything from 9,500 to 10,499
would round to our estimate of 10,000. when we do calculations we have to pay
attention to the number of sig figs
if we are adding or subtracting our
answer will have as many decimal places
as the value with the least number of
decimal places
if we are multiplying or dividing our
answer will have as many sig figs
as the value with the least number of sig figs
whatever our answer is we'll have to
round up or down
at the appropriate digit. 5 or higher
means round up
four or below means round down. let's check
comprehension
thanks for watching guys subscribe to my
channel for more tutorials
and as always feel free to email me